<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The second Adam being the second part, or branch of the comparison between the first, and the second Adam, in these words, so by the obedience of one, shall many be made righteous. By Thomas Bradley doctor of divinity, chaplaine to His late Majesty King Charles the First, and præbend of York. And there preached at Lent assizes holden there, 1667/8. Oxon. Exon.</title>
            <title>Nosce te ipsum. Part 2.</title>
            <author>Bradley, Thomas, 1597-1670.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1668</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 68 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29121</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4136A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R213087</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99825598</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99825598</idno>
            <idno type="VID">29984</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29121)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 29984)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1790:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The second Adam being the second part, or branch of the comparison between the first, and the second Adam, in these words, so by the obedience of one, shall many be made righteous. By Thomas Bradley doctor of divinity, chaplaine to His late Majesty King Charles the First, and præbend of York. And there preached at Lent assizes holden there, 1667/8. Oxon. Exon.</title>
                  <title>Nosce te ipsum. Part 2.</title>
                  <author>Bradley, Thomas, 1597-1670.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>55, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Stephen Bulkley, and are to be sold by Richard Lambert,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>York :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1668.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A continuation of Bradley's Nosce te ipsum.</note>
                  <note>Identified as Wing B4136 on UMI microfilm set "Early English books, 1641-1700".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Person and offices --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:29984:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Second Adam; BEING The Second Part, or Branch of the Compariſon between the firſt, and the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> in theſe Words, <hi>So by the Obedience of</hi> One, <hi>ſhall many be made Righteous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> Thomas Bradley <hi>Doctor of Divinity,</hi> Chaplaine to His late Majeſty King <hi>CHARLES</hi> the Firſt, and Praebend of <hi>York.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And there Preached at Lent Aſſizes holden there, 1667/8. <hi>Oxon. Exon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>YORK,</hi> Printed by <hi>Stephen Bulkley,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Richard Lambert,</hi> 1668.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:29984:2"/>
            <p>Imprimatur,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Joh. Garth wait, <hi>Reverendiſſimo in Chriſto Patri, ac Dom. Dom.</hi> Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chardo <hi>Archiepiſ.</hi> Eboracenſi, <hi>à Sacris Domeſticis.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Datum</hi> Epiſcopo-Thorpae, <date>Jun, 11.1668.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:29984:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Rom. 5.19.</hi>
                  </bibl> So by the obedience of one, ſhall many be made righteous.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IN opening of which words, we will obſerve the ſame Method which we did in our Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe upon the former, in theſe foure par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars. By conſidering firſt, <hi>Who was this One?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>What was this his obedience?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>How the benefit of it comes to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated to ſo many?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>What Righteouſneſs that is which they gaine by it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe foure particulars clearly offer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to our conſideration upon the firſt view of the Text: and ſo, they are an apt Reddition to the foure particulars we conſidered in the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> in the former branch of the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon between them.</p>
            <p>To the firſt then, <hi>Who was this One? What, Hath he no Name?</hi> Yes, The Prophet. <hi>Iſay</hi> tells you his Name, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9.6. <hi>His Name ſhall be called wonderfull, Counſellor, the mighty God, the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:29984:3"/>Father, the Prince of Peace, &amp;c.</hi> Yea, he had a Name aſſign'd him by the Father before he was borne, <hi>Math.</hi> 1.21. <hi>His Name ſhall be called</hi> Jeſus: For though he was borne in time, in the appointed time, in the <hi>fullneſs of time,</hi> Gal. 4.4. yet he had a being before all time; <hi>His goings out were from the beginning, and from everlaſting,</hi> Micha 5.2. <hi>Jacobs Shiloh, Balaams Starr, Daniels Meſſiah, Davids Branch,</hi> out of the Root of <hi>Jeſſe</hi> they all meet in this One: All along throughout the whole Scripture from end to end: There is a Veine, a Maſter Veine, wherein his blood doth run, and whereby he was made known to the Church in all the Ages and Generations of the World; in the Promiſes, and Propheſies, Types, and Figures, Sacraments, and Sacrifices, untill he came himſelfe in Perſon to fulfill them all, and by his holy Birth, Life, and Death, Reſurrection and Aſcenſion, to make them good, and to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe unto us the righteouſneſs in the Text mentioned. This is that <hi>One</hi> in the Text; in this <hi>One</hi> doe all theſe things meet, and concen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: The Apoſtle both frugally, and prudently ſet him forth unto us in this ſhort expreſſion of one word, one ſyllable, and that an indefinite
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:29984:3"/>too, for two reaſons, he had a double reach in it.</p>
            <p>Firſt, To put us upon a farther inquiry after him, that ſo we might come to be better ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with him, and to know him more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly in his Perſon, in his Natures, in his Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, in his Works, in his Miracles, and in the fruits and benefits of them all, as they are ſparſedly ſet forth in the holy Scriptures: <hi>Search the Scriptures, for in them you thinke to have eternall life, and they are they which teſtifie of me,</hi> ſaith himſelfe of himſelfe, <hi>John</hi> 5.39.</p>
            <p>Secondly, To teach us the ſingleneſs, the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularity, the Oneneſs (if you will) of this our Mediator; he is One and he is but One, he is alone, there is not another with him, he hath no partner in this great undertaking.</p>
            <p>And this Oneneſs in order to this great at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chieument conſiſts principally in theſe three things, he is <hi>One</hi> in theſe three reſpects.</p>
            <p>Firſt, In reſpect of his Filiation.</p>
            <p>Secondly, In reſpect of the Union of the two Natures, the Divine, and the Humane, in his One Perſon.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, In reſpect of the performance of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:29984:4"/>this great work of the Mediatorſhip. In all theſe reſpects he is <hi>One,</hi> and he is alone.</p>
            <p>Firſt, In reſpect of his Filiation; he is the onely begotten Sonne of the Father: God hath many Sons indeed; Angels are his Sons, <hi>Job</hi> 1. they are his Sons by Creation: The Saints are his Sons too, they are his Sons by Grace, by the Grace of Adoption. But this <hi>One</hi> in our Text, is a Sonne after a more pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar manner; he is his Sonne by eternall Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; <hi>His onely begotten Sonne,</hi> ſo S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>John</hi> 1.14. <hi>The Word was made Fleſh, and dwelt amongſt us, and we ſaw his glory, as the glory of the onely begotten Sonne of God, full of grace and truth:</hi> So we profeſs in the Apoſtolicall Creed, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, <hi>To beleeve in</hi> Jeſus Chriſt <hi>the onely begotten Sonne of God:</hi> ſo in <hi>John</hi> 3.16. In all which places, this addition, <hi>of the onely begotten Sonne,</hi> is not vaine, it is full of emphaſis, and doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly magnifie the tranſcendent love of the Father to the loſt Sons of <hi>Adam,</hi> that for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring of them, would part with his own Son, his onely Son, and give him up to ſuch hard conditions as he did, for their recovery. No marvaile, if the Evangeliſt reporting this, ſet it forth with a Note of admiration, <hi>John</hi> 3.16.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:29984:4"/>
               <hi>God ſo loved the World, that he gave his onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Sonne, to the end that whoſoever beleeveth in him ſhould not periſh, but have life everlaſting.</hi> Thoſe foure circumſtances in it, of <hi>Tantus, Tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillos, Tales,</hi> and <hi>Tanti,</hi> that ſo great a Majeſty ſhould look upon ſuch inconſiderable crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and thoſe ſo grievous ſinners, enemies, and diſobedient to doe ſo much for them, raiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes his love and goodneſs to that height, that is beyond the comprehenſion of Men, or Angels. When God, for the tryall of <hi>Abrahams</hi> Faith, layd ſo hard a Taske upon him, as to command him to offer up his onely Son in ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice to him, and ſaw he was ſo ready to obey him, as to build the Altar, to binde his Son to the Wood upon it, and to ſtretch forth his hand to kill him, he ſtayes his hand, <hi>It is enough</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>hold thy hand, for now I know that thou loveſt me, ſeeing thou wert willing to offer up thy onely Son in Sacrifice in obedience to my Word.</hi> If that were a ſufficient evidence of <hi>Abrahams</hi> love to God? upon how much ſtronger evidence may we conclude the love of God to the loſt Sons of <hi>Adam,</hi> which did not onely offer to offer up, but offered up indeed his <hi>One, and onely begotten Son</hi> a Sacrifice for their ranſome?</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:29984:5"/>
            <p> Secondly, This Oneneſs reſpects the Unity of his Perſon, conſiſting of two Natures, the Divine, and the Humane, yet both by hypoſtaticall uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſo united, as that they make up but one Chriſt, one Perſon, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>God Man,</hi> to be a fit Mediator between God and Man, and all this was neceſſary in all the particulars of it. Firſt, That he ſhould be God. Secondly, That he ſhould be Man. And thirdly, That both theſe ſhould be ſo united, as to become <hi>One.</hi> It was neceſſary that he ſhould be Man, that ſo he might punctually ſatisfie Divine Juſtice, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering for ſin in that Nature that had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted it. And it was neceſſary he ſhould be God, that by the Dignity of his Perſon, he might adde value to his ſufferings, and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, to make them ſatisfactory for the ſins of the whole World. It was neceſſary that he ſhould be Man, that he might have what to offer up to God in ſacrifice for us, a body capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of death and ſufferings, with blood to ſhed, without which there is no Redemption; and the God-head is impateible: Therefore ſaith he in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40.6. <hi>A body haſt thou prepared me, Heb.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>0.5. And it was neceſſary that he ſhould be God, that ſo by the Power of his Deïty, he
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:29984:5"/>might ſuſtaine the Humanity, under the great burden of his Fathers wrath, and death the conſequence of it, and by his own Power reſcue himſelfe by a Glorious Reſurrection, and a Triumphant Conqueſt over all the powers of darkneſs. It was neceſſary that he ſhould be Man, that ſo he might be a compaſſionate High Prieſt, ſenſible of our miſeries, and infirmities, and ſo become a more earneſt Advocate and Mediator for Man. And it was neceſſary that he ſhould be God, that ſo he might be fit to mediate with God for us: <hi>If one Man ſin againſt another, the Advocate ſhall pleade for him: But if a Man ſin againſt God, who ſhall pleade for him?</hi> Who, but <hi>One,</hi> that is God, like unto him? Therefore it was neceſſary that he ſhould be both, both God and Man, and both in <hi>One:</hi> Neither as meer Man, ſo compaſſionating the decayed Eſtate of the loſt Sons of <hi>Adam,</hi> as to neglect the Honour of the Deïty wronged and offended; nor as meer God, ſo tendering the Honour of the Deïty injuried and offended, as to neglect the deplorable Eſtate of Man kinde loſt, and undone; but as <hi>One</hi> that was both, that did partake of both, was near and deare to both, and both to him, he might lay an indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:29984:6"/>hand upon both, and ſo become between them, an equall and indifferent Mediator. In this Union we have that great Myſtery of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs ſo much magnified by S. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. Of <hi>God manifeſted in the Fleſh;</hi> that ſtupendious Myſtery, which the Angells themſelves doe with ſo great admiration and aſtoniſhment pry into, <hi>Of God in Chriſt, reconciling the World unto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,</hi> 2 Cor. 5.19. In this Union of the Divine and Humane Nature of the Mediator thus met together in this <hi>One</hi> Perſon, was that great Marriage made up in Heaven, the Banes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of were ſo long before Publiſhed on Earth by the Royall Prophet <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 85.10. <hi>Mercy and Truth are met together: Righteouſneſs and Peace have kiſſed each other.</hi> In this Union did <hi>Iſaiahs</hi> Twinns meet, the Childe, and the Son; <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9.6. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto us a Childe is borne, unto us a Sonne is given:</hi> The Childe was borne; but the Sonne was given; the Childe without a Father, the Sonne without a Mother; both in <hi>One,</hi> and both but <hi>One,</hi> this <hi>One</hi> in the Text, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>God Man,</hi> or <hi>Man God, Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, He is here ſtyled <hi>One,</hi> in reſpect of the great Worke he was to performe in the great Office of the Mediatorſhip, to make
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:29984:6"/>peace between God and Man, to make an at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonement, that is, to ſet them at <hi>One,</hi> which were before at ſuch a diſtance one from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in which work he was alone, he had no partners to aſſiſt him. There is but <hi>One Mediator</hi> between God and Man, the <hi>Man Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> 'Tis true, <hi>Moſes</hi> was a Mediator, <hi>when he ſtood in the gap between the living and the dead, to turne away wrath when it was gone forth, and the Plague was begun,</hi> Exod. 32. So are all the Saints and faithfull ſervants of the Lord, favourites of Heaven, which uſe the intereſt they have in God, for the good of the World, to intercede for them, to appeaſe his wrath, and to depre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate the evills which God threatneth to bring upon them for ſin, and for tranſgreſſion, for whoſe ſakes and Prayers, God is often prevailed with, to divert, or to ſuſpend, or to mitigate the Judgements which their ſins have called for; but theſe are Mediators of Interceſſion, not of Redemption: Of it the Prophet tells us, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 49.7. <hi>No man can deliver his brother, nor pay a Ranſome to God for him.</hi> Nor amongſt the Angells is there found a Mediator; Alas! they ſtood in need of a Mediator, as well as we, but found none: <hi>For he took not upon him
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:29984:7"/>the nature of Angels: but he took upon him the ſeed of</hi> Abraham, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.16. yea, even the good Angels ſtood in need of a Mediator, though not to recover them out of a loſt eſtate, yet to eſtabliſh them in that eſtate wherein they ſtand. No, nor among the ſacred Trinity is there found a Mediator beſides him: For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be true, <hi>Omnia opera Trinitatis ad extra ſunt indiviſa,</hi> as the Schooles ſpeak; and in the continuance of this great Goſpel deſigne, the wiſedome of the whole Trinity was ſet on worke, and every perſon in it did contribute to the laying of the plot: yet when it came to execution, by Divine diſpenſation, it fell to the Sonnes ſhare to execute it, to tranſact it, and in his Perſon to undertake, and go through with it. Of this the Prophet puts us in minde, or rather the Lord himſelfe by the Prophet, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63. <hi>I have troden the Wine preſs alone, and of the people there was none to help me,</hi> ver. 3. and again, <hi>ver.</hi> 5. <hi>And I looked, and there was none to help: and I wondred that there was none to uphold: therefore mine own arme helped me, and my wrath ſuſtained me.</hi> This is againe remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred by St. <hi>John</hi> in the fifth of the <hi>Revelations,</hi> under the notion of receiving, and opening a
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:29984:7"/>book with ſeven Seals: Firſt excluſively, <hi>verſe</hi> 3. <hi>None was found that could open it but he.</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly incluſively, <hi>ver.</hi> 5.6.7. <hi>Where he taketh the Book, looſeth the Seals, and openeth it, to the great joy and jubily of the Church, both Militant, and Triumphant:</hi> This the Church Triumphant preſently teſtifies, by breaking forth into his prayſe, in that their new Song, <hi>ver.</hi> 9. and by their Angelicall Doxology, <hi>verſes</hi> 11. and 12. <hi>Worthy is the Lambe that was killed, to receive power, and riches, and wiſedome, and honour, and glory, and prayſe.</hi> And the Church Militant joyne with them, <hi>ver.</hi> 13. <hi>Prayſe, and honour, and glory, and power, be unto him that ſitteth upon the Throne, and unto the Lambe for evermore.</hi> And let all thoſe that look for benefit by his Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torſhip, ſay <hi>Amen;</hi> and joyne with this Ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall Choyre in their Heavenly Hallelujahs, and ſay, <hi>Glory be to God on high, for this Peace on Earth purchaſed by the Mediator, and for the good will ſhewed to the Sonnes of Men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. And ſo we have done with this <hi>One</hi> in the Text, the Perſon by which our deliverance is wrought: We now come to conſider of the way and means by which he hath wrought it; &amp; the Text tells us, it was by Obedience, <hi>So by the Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of One.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:29984:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> But was this the onely way for the Mediator to work deliverance for the Sonns of <hi>Adam?</hi> Or was it ſuitable to the ſtate of ſo great a Perſon, of whom ſo glorious things are ſpoken, to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit himſelfe to ſuffering, and <hi>Obedience?</hi> Had he come down in State and Majeſty, with Power and great Glory, <hi>Riding upon the wings of the winde, attended with Legions of Angels and Arch-Angels, in flaming fire rendring vengeance to his enemies; treading upon the necks of Kings and Keſars; by ſtrong hand vanquiſhing the powers of darkneſs, and bearing down before him all oppoſite Power that did advance it ſelfe againſt his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; this had been an equipage well becomming the Prince of Glory, the King of Kings, and Lord of Lords?</hi> But for ſuch a Perſon ſo farr to leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen himſelfe, as to de-throne himſelfe, to ſtrip himſelfe of all thoſe Robes of Majeſty and Glory, which he enjoyed at the right hand of the Father, and to take upon himſelfe the forme of a ſervant, of an Infant, and to come downe from God to Man, from commanding Angels, to ſubmit to the commands of vile ſinners, and from thundering in Heaven, to cry in a Cradle, was ſuch a condeſcention, as may well afford matter of admiration and aſſoniſhment to Men
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:29984:8"/>and Angels. Yet ſo it was, and ſo it muſt be, or we had been all <hi>Children without Adoption,</hi> Gal. 4.4.5. It was the diſobedience of the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> and ours in him, that he came to anſwer for: And what better way to anſwer for diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, then by obedience? every evill is beſt expelled by 'its contrary: Will the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> in the pride of his heart aſpire to the very <hi>Zenith</hi> of Dignity, the <hi>Apex</hi> of Majeſty, and being but a man, will needs be like unto God? The ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> to expiate this ſin, muſt come downe to the very <hi>Nadir</hi> of humility, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God muſt become Man, that ſo he might make a recompence unto God for that his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate ambition, and ſo make his peace. Did the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> offend by Eating? By Faſting muſt the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> expiate that his intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance, <hi>Matth.</hi> 4. Did the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> abuſe his liberty and priviledges in Paradiſe? The ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> muſt make amends for it, by his Heremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall hardſhip in the Wilderneſs. Did the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> ſo puſillanimouſly betray himſelfe, and his, by yeelding to the ſuggeſtions and tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Devill? The ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payre that loſs and diſhonour, muſt encounter the Devill, and in faire cumbating vanquiſh him
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:29984:9"/>again and again, and ſo fully revenge the quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell of the firſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 4. Did the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> offend by diſobedience? By obedience muſt the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> ſatisfie for it, and ſo he did; for ſo ſaith the Text, <hi>By the Obedience of One.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are two things in this great tranſaction well worth our Obſervation. Firſt, How the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond <hi>Adam</hi> hath trac't the firſt all along ſtep by ſtep; and where ever he found the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> had endamag'd us, there doth he make a ſtand, and not paſs by till he hath repayred us: As <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.6. <hi>As I paſſed by thee, I ſaw thee in thy blood, &amp;c.</hi> The ſecond, How in this reparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he provides for us all along a remedy ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to our malady, a ſalve proper for the cure of the ſore, a ſatisfaction punctually anſwering the Juſtice of God for that ſin, by which we had offended it, as in the paſſages above in timated: See it farther more clearly and diſtinctly in this his obedience.</p>
            <p>There are three branches of this his obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, by which he hath ſet us free, and wrought out righteouſneſs for us. Firſt, The Obedience of his Birth. Secondly, The Obedience of his Life. Thirdly, The Obedience of his Death. Firſt, the Obedience of his Birth, in his holy
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:29984:9"/>Conception and Incarnation. Secondly, The Obedience of his Life, in his holy and unblame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Converſation. Thirdly, The Obedience of his Death, in his bitter Paſſion and Crucifixion; and theſe were all neceſſary, none of theſe three could have been ſpared: For three wayes we ſtood obnoxious unto Divine Juſtice.</p>
            <p>Firſt, For our Originall ſin, the ſin of our Nature, wherein we were conceived and borne.</p>
            <p>Secondly, For all our ſins of Omiſſion; and particularly, for fayling in performing the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the Covenant of Works, and of obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Commandement given in Paradiſe, in the mandatory part of it, upon which, Life, and Salvation was made over to us, in theſe words, <hi>Doe this, and thou ſhalt live.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, For all our ſins of Commiſſion, and particularly, for breaking his Commandement given in Paradiſe, in the minatory part of it; which ſaid, <hi>In the day that thou Eateth thereof, thou ſhalt dye the Death.</hi> In all theſe three re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, we were obnoxious to Divine Juſtice; We lay under Wrath, and under a ſentence of eternall Death; and from all theſe three, by theſe three parts of this his Obedience, are we ſet free. Firſt, By this Obedience, and Merit,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:29984:10"/>of his holy Conception and Incarnation, are we delivered from our Birth-ſinne, wherein we are conceived and borne; the holineſs of his Humane Nature conceived, and borne without ſin, being imputed unto us, that ſo by it, the impurity of ours, conceived and borne in ſin, may be cured, and healed, and done away.</p>
            <p>Secondly, By his Active Obedience in his moſt holy Life, which he led here on Earth, in the dayes of his fleſh, perfectly fulfilling the Law for us, hath he delivered us from all our ſins of Omiſſion, which was the ſecond way, by which we ſtood in danger of Divine Juſtice: For thus ſpeaks the Law, <hi>Curſed is every one that continueth not in every thing that is Written in the Book of the Law to doe it:</hi> This had we made impoſſible to be done by us; but done it muſt be for us, or we all undone. And this is done in the Active Obedience of this our Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator, and for this purpoſe was it, that he ſtayed ſo long upon Earth, among the Sonnes of Men; <hi>He dwelt among us,</hi> as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>John</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>John</hi> 1.14. full three and thirty years; ſome ſay more, neer fifty, grounding their conjecture upon thoſe words of the <hi>Jews,</hi> ſpoken to <hi>him, John</hi> 8.57. <hi>Thou art not yet fifty years old, and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:29984:10"/>haſt thou ſeen Abraham?</hi> But thirty we are ſure he was, when he entred upon his Miniſtery, what time ever he continued afterward; and this was neceſſary, that he might have a competent time to fulfill the Law, in all the parts and branches of it; and ſo, by performing the condition of the Covenant of Works for us, to reſtore us again to our right, to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Heaven, made over to us upon that condition.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, By his Paſſive Obedience hath he freed us from all our ſins of Commiſſion, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering the Law in the minatory part of it, which ſaid, <hi>The ſoule that ſinneth ſhall dye:</hi> And, <hi>In the day that thou eateſt, ſhalt thou dye the death.</hi> By ſuffering death, he hath taken off that ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of death, that was gone out againſt us; and by becomming a curſe for us, hath taken off that curſe that was upon us. And thus hath the Lord layd upon him the iniquities of us all, thus hath he borne our iniquities. By theſe three parts of his <hi>obedience,</hi> hath he anſwered for our diſobedience, and ſet us free from the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of Divine Juſtice, in all thoſe three wayes in which we ſtand obnoxious to it, though it coſt him deare.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:29984:11"/>
            <p> By his Originall Righteouſneſs, he hath freed us from our Originall ſin: By his Active Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, from all our ſins of Omiſſion: By his Paſſive Obedience, from all our ſins of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion. By his Active Obedience, he hath freed us, <hi>à poenâ damni,</hi> from the puniſhment of loſs. By his Paſſive, <hi>à poenâ ſenſus,</hi> from the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of paine. By his Paſſive Obedience, he hath reſcued us out of the jaws of Hell: And by his Active Obedience, he hath opened unto us the Gates of Heaven. This Active Obedience was ſatisfactory: And his Paſſive meritorious. And thus you ſee how he is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come unto us a perfect Saviour, and hath by theſe three parts of his obedience, wrought out for us plentifull redemption. Had any of theſe three been wanting, he had not wrought out for us plentifull redemption. Had our Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor onely dyed for us, been crucified, dead, and buried, he had not wrought out for us plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full redemption; he had onely ſatisfied the Law in the minatory part of it, and by this his Paſſive Obedience, ſo taken off the ſentence of death, that lay upon us; but he had not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by reſtored us unto life, nor to our right, and title to our forfeited Inheritance, he had ſtill
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:29984:11"/>left us obnoxious to divine Juſtice, for the breach of the Commandement in the mandatory part of it; which ſaid, <hi>Fac hoc, &amp; vives:</hi> doe this, and thou ſhalt live. Had the Mediator by his Active Obedience ſatisfied the Law, and ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled it in the mandatory part of it; and ſo by his holy Life, fulfilled, and performed the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the Covenant of Works for us; yet he had not wrought out for us plentifull redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, he had ſtill left us open to the Juſtice of God, for the ſin of our Nature, our Originall ſin, wherein we are conceived, and borne. But that he might work out for us plentifull redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, it was not enough for him, nor for us, that he ſhould be made a Man, as the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> was by Creation; but he muſt become a Child, an Infant, conceived in the Wombe, and borne into the World, after the ſame manner as other Children are (ſin onely excepted) that ſo he might begin the Cure of our Diſeaſe, where the Diſeaſe it ſelfe begins in the very Wombe, and that by the purity, and merit of his holy Conception and Incarnation, imputed unto us, the impurity of our Nature may be healed, and our Infants ſanctified, and purified in the Wombe, and from the Wombe, by the vertue
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:29984:12"/>and merit of the Conception, and Incarnation of the holy Child Jeſus: And therefore we doe with as much comfort confeſs and beleeve, <hi>That he was Conceived by the holy Ghoſt, and borne of the Virgin</hi> Mary: as, <hi>That he ſuffered for us under</hi> Pontius Pilate, <hi>was crucified, dead, and buried.</hi> They that lay all the ſtreſſe of our redemption, upon the death, and blood of Chriſt, doe not fully deliver the Doctrine of our redemption, they over-look the greateſt part of it, in the Active Obedience of his Life, and the Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of his Birth and Incarnation. They that lay it wholly upon his Active and Paſſive Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, doe not yet deliver the Doctrine of our Redemption fully, they overlook an eſſentiall part of it, in the Obedience of his Conception, and Incarnation. But the Apoſtle doth not overlook it, <hi>Phil</hi> 2. when he ſayes, <hi>That being in the forme of God, and thinking it no robbery to be equall with God: He took upon himſelfe the forme of a man, of a ſervant, of a childe, of an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant,</hi> which was in his Incarnation. And the Church doth not over look it, when it cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brates the prayſe of it with Admiration, in theſe words (of her deſpiſed Liturgy,) <hi>When thou tookeſt upon thee to deliver Man, thou didſt
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:29984:12"/>not abhorre the Virgins Wombe.</hi> There did the work of our Redemption begin, which was proſecuted all along, throughout his whole life, his death, buriall, and reſurrection: out of which, for a beleever to draw out of all the parts, and paſſages of it that comfort that they doe afford, and to apply them to thoſe ſeverall wants and maladies of his ſoule, for the ſupply and cure whereof they are moſt proper, is a point of high wiſedome, and gives unto the foule ſtrong conſolation, and full ſatisfaction. It is ſomething to know Chriſt Crucified in groſſe, <hi>That Jeſus Chriſt came into the World to ſave ſinners:</hi> This gives the Faith of adherence. But to know Chriſt more diſtinctly, in his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, his Natures, his Offices, and the executions of them, in all the parts of the precious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption he hath wrought out for us, and take out that merit and vertue, which they doe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford, and rightly to apply it to the ſeverall wants of our ſoules, for the reliefe whereof they are moſt proper; is much more comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and ſpeaks the Faith of aſſurance, when we are able to Reade in his Originall Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, the diſcharge of our Originall ſin; in his Incarnation, the purification of our Natures;
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:29984:13"/>in his birth, our new birth; in his Active Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, ſatisfaction for all our ſins of Omiſſion; in his Paſſive Obedience, a ſatisfaction for all our ſins of Commiſſion; in his ſtripes, our heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; in his condemnation, our abſolution; in his death, our life; in his buriall, our mortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; in his Reſurrection, and Aſcenſion, our Reſurrection, and Glorification. In the 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 4.32. we reade, how <hi>Eliſha</hi> going to revive the <hi>Shunamites</hi> Sonne, went into the Chamber where he lay, and there <hi>caſt himſelfe upon the Child, and layd his face to the childs face, and his eyes to the childs eyes, and his hands to the childs hands,</hi> and ſo applyed himſelfe unto the Child, part by part; and after a little ſpace, <hi>the Child neeſed ſeven times, and revived:</hi> So if we can by Faith, thus diſtinctly apply our ſelves unto this holy Child <hi>Jeſus,</hi> and him to us, in all the branches of this his Obedience, by which he hath wrought out deliverance for us; not the Child, but we, which before were dead in ſins and treſpaſſes, by vertue and grace derived from him, ſhall revive and live, the life of grace here, and of glory hereafter with him in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for overmore.</p>
            <p>And ſo we have done with the ſecond branch
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:29984:13"/>in the Reddition, to the firſt part of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon between the two <hi>Adams,</hi> ſhewing the means, by which he hath ſatisfied for the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience of the firſt <hi>Adam;</hi> That was, <hi>By Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</hi> We now come to the third, wherein we are to conſider, The Perſons that are benefited by it, and the Text ſayes, <hi>They are many. So by the Obedience of One, ſhall many be made Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here doe ariſe three Queſtions.</p>
            <p>Firſt, How the obedience of one, can ſatisfie for the diſobedience of another? What Juſtice there is in this? Or how it can ſtand good in Law?</p>
            <p>Secondly, If it doe ſo? yet how the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of one, ſhould ſtand good, to anſwer for the diſobedience of ſo many?</p>
            <p>And thirdly, How man they are, that are to be benefited by it?</p>
            <p>To the firſt, I anſwer, The obedience, and righteouſneſs of one, may ſtand good for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, where theſe three things concurr; or in theſe three caſes.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, With the conſent of all perſons con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, where all parties concerned are agreed.</item>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:29984:14"/>
               <item>Secondly, Where there is ſuch a Union between the one and the other, that what is done to, or for, or by the one, is done by the other alſo.</item>
               <item>Thirdly, Where there is a proportion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the offence of the one, and the ſatisfaction of the other.</item>
            </list>
            <p>For the firſt, There are but thee Perſons con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd, The Father, the Sonne, and <hi>Adam,</hi> with his Progeny. That the Father is agreed, it is cleare, <hi>John</hi> 3.16. <hi>He gave his Sonne.</hi> Gal. 4.4. <hi>He ſent his Sonne.</hi> That the Sonne is agreed, is as cleare, <hi>John</hi> 10.15. <hi>I lay down my life for my ſheep.</hi> And again, <hi>ver.</hi> 18. more fully, <hi>No man taketh it from me, I lay it down of my ſelfe.</hi> And that <hi>Adam,</hi> and his Sons are agreed, is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all queſtion, whoſe caſe it is, and who onely receive the benefit of it. And thus 'tis good even in Law, That the obedience of one, may ſtand good for another, upon this firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration; and if it were not good in Law, 'tis good in Goſpel.</p>
            <p>The ſecond conſideration upon which 'tis good, is this, If there be ſuch a neerneſs, and union between him that performeth this obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and thoſe for whom it is performed,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:29984:14"/>that what is done by him, may be reputed as done by themſelves. We reade of a King of the <hi>Locrenſes,</hi> which made a Law, <hi>That whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever of his Subjects was found guilty of Adultery, ſhould have both his eyes put out.</hi> It ſo fell out, that the firſt that was deprehended in that crime, was his own Sonne; it was grievous to him that his Sonne ſhould loſe both his Eyes; and as grievous, that he ſhould not execute Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice upon the tranſgreſſion of his own Law: For mitigating between both, he put out one of his Sons Eyes, and one of his own; and this was accounted good Juſtice; and is the very caſe in the Text; onely with this difference, That he took upon himſelfe but halfe the puniſhment; our Mediator took it all, and wholly to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, to ſet us free; and Chriſt, and we, are one. <hi>Lord have mercy upon me,</hi> (ſaith the <hi>Canaanitiſh</hi> Woman, <hi>Matth.</hi> 15.22.) <hi>my Daughter is grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouſly vexed with a Devill;</hi> implying, That the mercy which was ſhewed unto her <hi>Daughter,</hi> was ſhewed unto her ſelfe, her Daughter, and ſhe, were one: Such is the Union between Chriſt, and thoſe that are Chriſts; ſo neer, that it amounts rather to an Identity, then an Union. If <hi>Saul</hi> be travailing to <hi>Damaſcus, to perſecute the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:29984:15"/>Members;</hi> the <hi>Head</hi> looks down from Heaven, and complains, <hi>Saul, Saul, why perſecuteth thou me? Acts</hi> 9.4. As the Husband with the Wife, the Branches with the Vine, the Members with the Body, are one; even ſo is Chriſt, with all that belong unto him: Take it in the Apoſtles words, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.12. <hi>As the Body is one, and hath many Members, and all the Members of the Body, which is one, though they be many, yet are but one body: even ſo is Chriſt.</hi> Where note, That the word Chriſt here, is not perſonally to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, as repreſenting the Perſon of Chriſt; but it is, <hi>Nomen collectivum,</hi> a collective name, and takes in to it, together with Chriſt, all the Saints, all beleevers, the whole Church of Chriſt under Chriſt their Head; all which together with him, make up but one body, one Chriſt, unto whom he vouchſafes his own name, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with himſelfe, even ſo is Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And there are three tyes, by which this Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is made up, and they are brought ſo neer to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. Firſt, By the bond of Faith. Secondly, By the bond of the Spirit. Thirdly, By the bond of Love. By theſe three bonds, are they united together, as by a three-fold cord, not eaſily broken. Firſt, By Faith we aſcend up to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:29984:15"/>Heaven, and lay hold on Chriſt. Secondly, By the Spirit, Chriſt deſcends from Heaven to Earth, and layes hold on us. And thirdly, By Love, we meet, as it were, between Heaven and Earth, and there cloſe with mutuall imbraces. Chriſt in his Incarnation took our Nature upon him, and ſo was made partaker of the Humane Nature. Then he renews us by his Grace, and ſo in our Regeneration, we are made partakers of the <hi>Divine Nature,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4. And that's ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way, by which this Union is made up, and we are brought ſo neer. And this is a Doctrine full of <hi>Grace and Truth, and worthy by all means to be received.</hi> For from this Union, there flowes a Communion between Chriſt, and his; our ſins are layd upon him, and he hath ſatisfied for them; his righteouſneſs is layd upon us, and we are juſtified by it, being thus united unto him, and he to us; we draw Vertue from him, as the branches doe from the root, and Influence, as the Members doe from the Head, whereby we are able to live that life, that is according to godlineſs, and walk in ſome conformity to him. By vertue of this Union, we derive Grace from him: <hi>Out of his fulneſs we all receive, and Grace for Grace,</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 16. By vertue of this Union,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:29984:16"/>Chriſt is ours, and with him all his merit, righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, and obedience, as in the Text; And ſo, <hi>By the obedience of</hi> One, <hi>are many made righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, It is not unreaſonable, That the odedience of one, ſhould benefit another; if the diſobedience of one, may prejudice ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: but we ſee, the diſobedience of the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> did prejudice others: It is therefore but equitable, That the obedience of the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> ſhould benefit others, depending upon him: <hi>Alter in ſemine, alter in ſanguine:</hi> and as the one by his ſeed brought in death; ſo the other by his blood, might reſtore to life; that the blood of the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> ſhould be as ſove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne to ſalve, and to ſave, as the ſeed of the firſt was to wound, and to deſtroy: And let this ſuffice for ſatisfying the firſt Query.</p>
            <p n="2">2 But the ſecond enquires furrher; How the obedience of one, ſhould anſwer for the diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of ſo many? How ſo many ſhould be ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified, and made righteous <hi>by the obedience of this One?</hi> And that's anſwered in theſe two rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. The firſt drawne from the Dignity of the Perſon obeying, which was of that high excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency, that it made his obedience, and ſuffering
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:29984:16"/>of that value, that was ſufficient for the ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyings of the ſins, and ranſoming of the ſoules of the whole world; the obedience which he performed, was the obedience of that Perſon which was God, as well as Man, <hi>and thought it no robbery to be equall with God:</hi> That blood which was ſhed for us, was the blood of that Perſon, which was God, as well as Man: Of this Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance, St. <hi>Peter</hi> puts us in minde, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.18. <hi>Knowing that you were not Redeemed with corruptible things, us ſilver and gold: but with the precious blood of Chriſt, as of a Lambe unſpotted, and undefiled.</hi> To which, if you adde, the ſtrangeneſs of his obedience, humiliation, and ſufferings, with the freeneſs of them, <hi>He became obedient,</hi> Phil. 2.8. <hi>obedient unto death, even the death of the Croſs.</hi> In his Incarnation, <hi>He did not abhorre the Virgins Wombe.</hi> In his Crucifixion, <hi>He was in the forme of a ſervant for our ſakes;</hi> yea, <hi>of a Malefactor: He was numbred among tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſors: He was wounded for our tranſgreſſions: The chaſtiſement of our peace lay upon him, that by his ſtripes, we might be healed.</hi> All theſe circumſtances add ſtill to the price, and value of his ſufferings, and obedience, to make it infinitely ſatisfacto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and meritorious, for the remiſſion of the ſins,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:29984:17"/>and the ranſomeing of the ſouls, of the whole World. The ſecond Reaſon is drawn from the conſideration of the capacity in which the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator ſtood, when he performed this obedience, and wrought out righteouſneſs for us: In this great tranſaction, he ſtood not as a ſingle Perſon, but as a repreſentative; he acted not for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, but for all beleevers, for the whole body of the Church, whereof he is the Head. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the Title of this Treatiſe, wherein he is ſtiled, <hi>The Stock, and Root of all his Race,</hi> the Head of his body, the Church, from which part every branch, every member deriveth, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveth grace, vertue, ſtrength, and influence, righteouſneſs and life, there being abundantly ſufficient for all, and in whom, and with whom, whatſoever he doth, and ſuffereth for them, in this capacity, they doe it, and ſuffer it alſo. Hence are thoſe frequent expreſſions in the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, wherein, we are ſaid <hi>to be in him, and he in us,</hi> John 10. <hi>We are elected in him,</hi> Epheſ. 1.4. <hi>Adopted in him,</hi> ver. 5. <hi>Circumciſed in him,</hi> Col. 2.12. <hi>Suffer with him,</hi> Rom. 8.17. <hi>Buried with him,</hi> Col. 2.13. <hi>Riſen with him,</hi> Col. 3.1. <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat in him,</hi> Col. 2.10. <hi>Suffer with him,</hi> Col. 1.24. Yea, <hi>Crucified with him,</hi> Gal. 2.20. When
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:29984:17"/>Chriſt did, &amp; ſuffered thoſe things as Mediator for us; we did, and ſuffered them in him, and ſo the obedience is imputed unto us, as ours, and is ours, <hi>Quo ad uſum, &amp; fructum,</hi> as to the uſe, and fruit of it, as well as if all had been done and ſuffered in our own perſons, and better too. And thus you ſee, how it may ſtand with Reaſon and Juſtice, That one may be Juſtified, by the obedience of another, and, <hi>By the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of One, many made righteous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. And this brings in the third Query, <hi>How many there may be?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſ. <hi>Even as many as beleeve in his name,</hi> John 3.16. <hi>As many as doe receive him upon Goſpel termes,</hi> John 1. <hi>As many as come in unto him, that they may have life:</hi> The offer of grace is made to all, without exception, though to none without condition; <hi>Ho, every one that thirſteth, let him come,</hi> Iſa. 55.1. <hi>God is no</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptor <hi>of perſons: but in every Nation, he that feareth God, and worketh righteouſneſs, is accepted of him,</hi> Acts 10.34. <hi>God would have all Men to be ſaved, and to come to the knowledge of the truth,</hi> 1 Tim. 2.4. <hi>He is the Saviour of all, eſpecially of them that beleeve,</hi> 1 Tim. 4.10. Thus generally the Promiſes run, in univerſall termes, that no
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:29984:18"/>man ſhould deſpaire; yet generally with ſome intimation too, of ſome duty on our parts, that no man may preſume. You may expect here, that I ſhould fall upon the point of Univerſall Redemption; but I ſhall forbeare it in this place, eſpecially having Treated more largely upon that Subject, in a Diſcourſe upon it out of <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9.6. and Printed at <hi>Oxford</hi> in 1650. unto which I referre. In the interim, thus much I will here declare of my Judgement in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, That I am perſwaded, that when the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> took our Nature upon him, and in it, wrought our righteouſneſs for us, there was no Son of the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> but he did ſomething for him, ſo much, as that he ſhall never periſh eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, in the lake of everlaſting burnings, unleſs he forfeit his ſalvation a ſecond time. What think you of that of St. <hi>Peter?</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1. <hi>There ſhall be falſe teachers among you, which ſhall bring in damnable Hereſies, even denying the Lord that bought them, and ſo bring upon themſelves ſwift damnation.</hi> There are falſe Teachers that bring in Hereſies, damnable Hereſies, that brings upon themſelves damnation, ſwift damnation; and yet the Text ſayes, even of theſe, <hi>That the Lord had bought them. How could this be?</hi> but that
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:29984:18"/>they ſold themſelves again, and forfeited their ſalvation a ſecond time; and therefore are true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſaid, <hi>To bring upon themſelves damnation.</hi> Theſe are they of which the Apoſtle ſayes, <hi>They are twice dead, pluckt up by the roots,</hi> Jude 12. once in the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> and now in the ſecond too, and ſo pluckt up by the roots, never to grow again. Againe, we are to be advertiſed, That though the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> then did ſomething for all, and all Nations; yet he did not doe for all alike. What is the meaning of that Parable in the Goſpel, of the Kings taking a farr Journey, and committing his Talents in truſt to his ſervants, or Factors, delivered them to them, in ſuch a different proportion, <hi>To one, but one Talent; to another two; to another five?</hi> Who is he that hath the one Talent, but the <hi>Heathen,</hi> which hath nothing to traffique withall, but the Law, and light of Nature? Who is he that hath the two Talents, but the <hi>Jew,</hi> which beſides it, hath the Law of <hi>Moſes?</hi> And who is he, that hath the five Talents, but the Chriſtian, which to both thoſe, hath the Law of Grace, the glorious Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt? It cannot be imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that the Kings returning to take their Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts, will require an equall account of them
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:29984:19"/>all, but according to their Receits. <hi>To whom much is given, of him much ſhall be required: and to whom leſs is given, of him leſs ſhall be required.</hi> God is a mercifull Creditor, and will require according to what a man hath, and not according to what he hath not.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Again, We are to be informed, That there are degrees of ſalvation, and of damnation too, though all are concluded under two names, of Heaven and Hell, of ſalvation and damnation; yet in both theſe, there are infinite degrees, and different proportions: <hi>There is one glory of the Sunne, another of the Moone, and another glory of the Starrs; for one Starr differeth from another in glory,</hi> 1 Cor. 15. And in reſpect of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>There are, that ſhall be beaten with fewer ſtripes; and there are that ſhall be beaten with more ſtripes.</hi> And although the higheſt degree of Goſpel-Salvation, be but the portion of a few, as our Saviour tells us, in compariſon of thoſe that periſh; yet there are many more, that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to ſome degrees of ſalvation, both in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the evill they are delivered from, and of the happineſs they are tranſlated too, which coms farr ſhort of the higheſt degree of happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, in the Kingdom of Heaven. And although
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:29984:19"/>our bleſſed Lord, which beſt knew it, tells us, <hi>That the way that leads to life is narrow, and the gate ſtreight, and ſo, few they be that finde it:</hi> yet himſelfe there declares himſelfe, that he ſpake it comparatively; in compariſon of <hi>the wide gate, and broad way, that leads to deſtruction,</hi> and of the multitude of paſſengers that travaile thither in it: but otherwiſe, if they be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered in themſelves, they are ſo many, as it is beyond all Arithmetick to number them. The Evangelicall Prophet <hi>Iſay,</hi> ſpeaking of the cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the Gentiles, ſeeth as in a Viſion, the multitudes of the Nations, from all quarters, making in to the ſtandard of Chriſt, and throng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in to Mount Sion, the embleme of the Church, with great zeale and earneſtneſs, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60. <hi>Who are theſe that come as a cloud, and as doues to the windows of the Sanctuary?</hi> v. 8. <hi>The multitude of the Sea ſhall be converted,</hi> ver. 5. He reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth the multitude of the converts to the Sea, to Clouds, to flocks of Sheep, to Caravans of Camels, &amp;c. from <hi>Midian,</hi> from <hi>Kedar,</hi> from <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baioth,</hi> from <hi>Arabia,</hi> from <hi>Sheba,</hi> from all quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, comming in to Chriſt. And ſuitable to this Viſion of the Prophet, is that Doxology of the Church Triumphant, which they Sing in the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:29984:20"/>honour of Chriſt, and giving glory to him, in <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.9. <hi>Thou art worthy to take the Book, and to open the ſeven ſeales of it: becauſe thou waſt killed, and haſt redeemed us unto God by thy blood, out of every Kindred, and Tongue, and People, and Nation.</hi> Neither does it ſtand with the glory of the Propheſies of old, nor ſuits with the famous promiſes made unto the Fathers of the glory of the Chriſtian Church; nor with the price of Chriſts blood, nor is it anſwerable to his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe made by it, nor with the abundance of Gods free grace, nor with the ſpatiouſneſs of the Heavens, appointed for the habitations of the bleſſed; ſpaces, that no man can meaſure for multitudes, that no man can number, that the number of the Sons of <hi>Adam</hi> that returne, ſhould be ſo ſmall, as ſome would perſwade us. But for that, we may not take upon us to mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the bounds of the Caeleſtiall Paradiſe, nor to tell the manſions that are in our Heavenly Fathers Houſe and Kingdom, which Chriſt hath prepared for his redeemed ones. It ſhall be our wiſedom, to make it our care, to ſecure unto our ſelves a roome among them, that we may be in the number of thoſe many in the Text, that we may fill up the places of the Apoſtate
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:29984:20"/>Angels, and that the number of the redeemed ones may be ſo much the greater, by ſo many ſoules, at leaſt, as are here preſent. And ſo we have done with the third particular, in the Red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to the firſt branch of the compariſon, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the firſt, and the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> wherein was conſidered the number of thoſe which are benefited <hi>by the obedience of this One Man:</hi> And the Text ſayes, <hi>They were many.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We come now to the fourth, and laſt parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular: Wherein we are to conſider, What that benefit is, which by this his obedience, they doe reape, and receive: And the Text ſayes, <hi>That by it they are made righteous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where Note, That they doe not leape from ſin to ſalvation immediately, and at one jumpe; but from ſin to righteouſneſs, they muſt take that in their way, before they come to happineſs. In <hi>Rome</hi> there were two Temples of much note, the Temple of Honour, and the Temple of Vertue; but they were ſo plac't, that no man could goe into the Temple of Honour, but he muſt paſs through the Temple of Vertue to it. Vertue is the way to Honour, ſo is Grace to Glory, Holineſs to Happineſs, Righteouſneſs to Life: <hi>Whom he juſtified, them he alſo glorified,</hi>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:29984:21"/>Rom. 8.30. but firſt juſtified, before glorified, they muſt paſs through that dore, before they can enter into Glory.</p>
            <p>Note ſecondly, That the Text ſayes, <hi>They ſhall be made righteous;</hi> they were not ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, we are not righteous of our ſelves, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not make our ſelves ſo, we muſt be made ſo, if ever we be ſo: Alas! of our ſelves we are grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous ſinners, <hi>altogether borne in ſin,</hi> John 9. <hi>Full of ſin, full of corruption, children of wrath by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> Epheſ. 2.2. Neither in this caſe can we help our ſelves, neither are we willing to help our ſelves, becauſe 'tis naturall to us, and in us, we pleaſe our ſelves in it, it is ſweet unto us, <hi>We hugg it in our boſomes, and hide it under our tongues,</hi> as <hi>Zophar</hi> ſpeaks in <hi>Job:</hi> Much power and grace is there required, and put forth to part us, to take us off from our ſins and corruptions, and them from us, to change our natures, and to renew us; It is no leſs than another Creation, yea, a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er work to make us righteous, then was at firſt to make us men; you ſee here what ſtrange obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience was performed to the effecting of it, and how much the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> hath done for us, in making us by ſuch his obedience righteous, <hi>(Tantae molis erat.)</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:29984:21"/>
            <p> And there is a three fold righteouſneſs, which by this his three-fold <hi>obedience</hi> he hath wrought out, and purchaſed for us, and obteyned to us.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The righteouſneſs of Juſtification.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The righteouſneſs of Sanctification.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The righteouſneſs of Glorification.</p>
            <p>For there is a Juſtifying righteouſneſs: And there is a Sanctifying righteouſneſs: And there is a Glorifying righteouſneſs. The firſt of theſe is perfect, but not inherent. The ſecond is inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, but not perfect. The third is both perfect, and inherent. The firſt of theſe, is the perfect, pure, and unſpotted righteouſneſs of Chriſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted unto us by grace, and received by Faith, with which the beleever being clothed, as <hi>Jacob, in the Robes of his elder brother,</hi> appears in the ſight of the Father, acceptable, and amiable: This is that righteouſneſs which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſo highly magnifieth, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.8. <hi>I eſteeme all to be but loſs, and droſs, that I may win Chriſt, and be found in him, not having mine own righteouſneſs which is by the Law, but that which is through the Faith in Chriſt, even the righteouſneſs which is of God by Faith.</hi> This is the righteouſneſs, which the ſame Apoſtle writes of to the <hi>Romans, Rom.</hi> 1.16. <hi>I am not aſhamed of the Goſſel of Chriſt, for
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:29984:22"/>it is the power of God unto ſalvation.</hi> How come's it to be ſo? Becauſe therein is the righteouſneſs of God revealed, by which beleevers are juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and ſaved. Of this righteouſneſs, doe I underſtand that, of which <hi>Elihu</hi> ſpeaks in <hi>Job,</hi> and to <hi>Job,</hi> 33.23. and of <hi>Job</hi> too, or any other in <hi>Jobs</hi> caſe, <hi>So ſick and ſo weak, that his ſoule draweth neer to the pit, and his life to the buriers,</hi> (ſo ſome Tranſlations reade it) <hi>then for an inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preter,</hi> a wiſe and faithfull Paſtor, to comfort, and to counſell him, to take his Confeſſion, and to give him Abſolution, for ſo much doe the words import: <hi>If there be an interpreter, one of a thouſand, to declare unto Man his righteouſneſs; then will he have mercy upon him, and will ſay: Deliver his ſoule from the pit, I have accepted of a ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome:</hi> that is, in the righteouſneſs of Chriſt, here called <hi>Mans righteouſneſs;</hi> as in the place before mentioned, it was called, <hi>The righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God,</hi> and very truely both: It is <hi>the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of God,</hi> becauſe it was wrought out in the Perſon of the Mediator, which is God: And it is, <hi>The righteouſneſs of Man</hi> too; becauſe being imputed unto him by Grace, and received by Faith, it becoms his own. This is the firſt righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs which we doe obtain, by the merit of
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:29984:22"/>the obedience of our Mediator; and this is the righteouſneſs we muſt build upon, for our Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification, Life, and Salvation, and well may: for this righteouſneſs is perfect, pure, abſolute, and compleat: this righteouſneſs will hold out; this righteouſneſs will abide the tryall, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent us with boldneſs, not onely before the Throne of Grace, but before the Throne of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice; being clothed with it, we ſhall appear un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blameable, without ſpot or wrinkle. The Lord will have nothing to charge us withall; but in this righteouſneſs, we ſhall finde wherewith to anſwer him: In this righteouſneſs we have all that we ſhould have, we are all that we ſhould be, we have done all that we ſhould doe, we have ſuffered all that we ſhould ſuffer. <hi>In him we are compleat,</hi> Col. 2.16. We ſtand in his ſight, as holy, as innocent, as pure, as perfect, as righteous, as the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> did in his Creation, before the Fall: Nay, may I not ſay more, as the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> in his humanity, in whoſe righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs it is that we ſhall appear?</p>
            <p>Hold faſt this Goſpel Truth, and lay it up againſt an evill day, when thou art caſt downe with ſenſe of ſinne, and feare of wrath, when ſtingings of Conſcience affright thee, and the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:29984:23"/>terrors of the Almighty make thee afraid; which way wilt thou turne thee for reliefe? where wilt thou look for peace? If in thy righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of Sanctification, there ſhalt thou ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver finde it; the holyeſt Saint on Earth, in this caſe, if he ſeek for peace in the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his Sanctification, he ſhall never finde it, ſo weak is our Sanctification at the beſt, ſo ſtrong our corruption, ſo many the infirmities, ſo fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent the faylings, yea, and fallings too, even of the beſt, that in their Sanctification, they can never finde peace, but the farther they ſeek for it there, the farther ſhall they be from find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that which they ſeek for. When the ſoule turnes, and asks, <hi>What peace?</hi> The Conſcience anſwers, <hi>What peace, while theſe thy ſins and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions remaine in ſuch abundance? It looks for peace, but behold trouble; for ſecurity, but behold diſquietneſs, and feare.</hi> But then have recourſe to your Juſtification, to this righteouſneſs of Chriſt imputed unto you by free grace, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by Faith, and there you will finde it, thence will follow peace; <hi>Being juſtified by Faith. we have peace with God,</hi> Rom. 5.1. and peace with our own Conſciences too. There is nothing can ſtill the crying, nor ſtop the bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:29984:23"/>of a wounded Conſcience, but onely th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>That Chriſt is the Lord our Righteouſneſs: and that by his Obedience,</hi> not by our own, <hi>we are made righteous,</hi> and this will doe it: This, this alone will anſwer all objections, that can be caſt in, to diſturbe our peace, <hi>That the chaſtiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our peace was layd upon him:</hi> This is the firſt righteouſneſs we gaine by the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of our Mediator, The righteouſneſs of Juſtification; this is perfect, but not inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is, The righteouſneſs of Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication; this is inherent, but not perfect: When God is pleaſed by his ſpirit of Grace, to ſanctifie and renew us, to change our natures, to take us out of the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> and to Plant us into the ſecond, to take us out of the ſtate of Nature, and to ſet us into a ſtate of Grace, by mortifying our corruptions, ſubduing our luſts, and inordinate affections, deſtroying that body of ſinne that dwelleth in our Members, fireing out all thoſe carnall luſts and affections, that are in us by the ſpirit of Judgement, and the ſpirit of burning: and then in the roome of them, to infuſe into our hearts holy habits, gracious diſpoſitions, propenſions, and inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:29984:24"/>which is our habituall holineſs, which remaining in us as principles of Liſe, from them there doe dayly flow gratious actions, ſuitable to them, expreſt in our Works, our Words, our Walkings, our Dealings, and dayly Converſation, which is our actuall holineſs, both concurring to make up this our righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Sanctification.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Note. </seg>
               </label> Where Note by the way, That theſe two righteouſneſſes, the righteouſneſs of Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the righteouſneſs of Sanctification ever goe together, <hi>Whom he juſtifieth, them he ſanctifieth,</hi> Rom. 8.30. Where ever God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoweth his Sonne to juſtifie, there he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoweth his Spirit to ſanctifie, ſooner or later, more or leſs. In the I'emple, there was a Laver, as well as an Altar; the Altar for Sacrifice, pointing out our redemption by the blood of Chriſt: The Laver, for Waſhing, pointing out our Sanctification by the Spirit of Chriſt. We muſt be Waſhed in the one, if we will be Sprinkled by the other. Chriſt at his Cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixion, being pierced by <hi>Longinus</hi> with a ſpeare, <hi>ſhed out of his pretious ſide, both Water and Blood.</hi> There was a Myſtery in it, the Blood ſignify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our Redemption by the Blood of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer:
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:29984:24"/>The Water, our Sanctification, by the Spirit of holineſs: There was water for our ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution; blood for our abſolution: water for our cleanſing; blood for our redeeming: he is not redeemed by that blood, which is not waſhed by that water; <hi>If I waſh thee not, thou haſt no part in me,</hi> John 13.8. Out of that Fountaine, the ſide of Chriſt, did ſpring both the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Chriſtian Church, <hi>Baptiſme, and the Lords Supper:</hi> The former is unto us, as the Laver in the Law; the latter, as the Altar: The former, the Sacrament of our regenerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; the latter of our redemption: The for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, ſealing up unto us our waſhing, and clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, in the Laver of regeneration; the latter, our atonement upon the Altar of our Redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, (let not the word offend you) by way of alluſion, at leaſt, you may allow it: but you muſt not paſs by the former, if you look for benefit by the latter: All the waſhings, clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, purgings, and purifyings under the Law, did but typically teach, and declare, the waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, cleanſing, and ſanctifying of Beleevers, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Goſpel, ſo much called for every where, <hi>Waſh your hands ye ſinners, and purge your hearts, ye wavering minded,</hi> James 4.8. <hi>This is the will
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:29984:25"/>of God, even your ſanctification,</hi> 1 Theſ. 41 3. <hi>Caſt off the old man, with his corrupt luſts, and put on the new man, which after God is created, in true holineſs and righteouſneſs,</hi> Epheſ. 4.22. <hi>Be ye holy, as I am holy,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.16. <hi>Follow peace and holineſs, without which, no man ſhall ſee the Lord,</hi> Heb. 12.14. Our God is a holy God: <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> is a holy City: the Inhabitants that dwell there are holy Saints: the exerciſes there uſed, are holy exerciſes. Into it may no un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane thing enter. All things call for holineſs at our hands, if ever we hope to come to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. The Apoſtle in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Colleſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Giveth thanks to the Father, that he had made them meet to be partakers of the Inheritance with the Saints in light,</hi> Col. 1.12. implying, That as we are in the ſtate of nature, and in the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> we are not meet for it. Before we be meet to be partakers of the Inheritance, with the Saints in light, we muſt be children of the light, and walk in the light. If ever we mean to inhabite in that holy City, we muſt here get into the Suburbs of it, and learne the Language of <hi>Canaan,</hi> which there they ſpeak. If ever we mean to beare a part in that Heavenly Choyre, in ſinging Hallelujahs <hi>to him that ſitteth upon the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:29984:25"/>Throne;</hi> we muſt here ſet our Harps, and our Hearts in Tune to it: We muſt get grace, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we can come to glory; righteouſneſs, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we can attaine to bleſſedneſs, even the righteouſneſs of Sanctification, before we can attaine to the righteousneſs of Glorification, and ſo we ſhall be meet for it: That makes us capable of it, that leads to it, even at the next remove: Which is the next particular, and the laſt to be ſpoken of; ſhewing the third ſort of righteouſneſs, of which, by the obedience of the Mediator, beleevers are made partakers:</p>
            <p>The righteouſneſs of Glory: And this ſhall be both perfect and inherent, when all ſin, as well as ſorrow, ſhall flee away, all corruption ſhall be aboliſhed: There ſhall be no more Devill to tempt, nor world to allure, nor fleſh to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw; but we ſhall with free, and full conſent of heart and will, ſerve, and laud, and magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the living Lord, and rejoyce in his preſence for evermore: where we ſhall arrive at the end of our hopes, the full fruition of God in the beatificall viſion, in whoſe light we ſhall ſee light, and we ſhall ſhine in the Kingdom of the Father, with Angelicall brightneſs, and perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, our ſouls ſhall acquieſce, <hi>In ultimo fine,</hi> in
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:29984:26"/>the fruition of the chiefeſt good, beyond which, there is nothing to be attained, nothing to be deſired, where God ſhall be to our underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Sunne of light, to our affections a Sea of love, to our wills abundance of peace: We ſhall drinke of the pleaſures of the Celeſtiall Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, as out of a River, and be filled with thoſe joyes, which are in his preſence unſpeakable, and glorious: We ſhall leave the dunghill of this inferiour world, with all the corruptions which are in it through luſt, and be taken up in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>third Heavens, and to the City of the living God, the Celeſtiall</hi> Jeruſalem; <hi>and to the company of innumerable Angels; and to the Aſſembly, and Congregation of the firſt borne, whoſe names are written in Heaven; and to God the Judge of all; and to the ſpirits of juſt men made perfest<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and to Jeſus Chriſt the Mediator, whom though we have not ſeen we love; but then we ſhall ſee him face to face, and our love and joy ſhall abound and we ſhall attaine to the end of our hopes, in the beginning of our happineſs,</hi> that never ſhall have end. <hi>Quando erit ille dies, quando erit illa dies?</hi> When will the day be, when that day ſhall be? How ſhould we love, and long for this appearance, and rejoyce even under the hope of this glory? Who that
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:29984:26"/>hath this hope, would not with St. <hi>Paul, Deſire to be diſſolved, that be may be with Chriſt?</hi> Phil. 1.23. Oh, if we ſhould but let looſe our ſoules, and turn them out, as <hi>Noah</hi> did his <hi>Dove,</hi> by divine contemplation, to ſore up to the third heavens, and there take a view of the joyes and glory of the Celeſtiall Paradiſe; how would it take us off from theſe vile things here below? How would it draw up our thoughts, to the ſeeking, and affecting of the things that are above? from the ſollicitous care of ſeeking after the treaſures of wickedneſs, which profit nothing; to the lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up of treaſures in Heaven, <hi>where neither moth nor ruſt can corrupt, nor theeves break through to ſteale; from ſeeking after the pleaſures of ſin which are but for a ſeaſon, to ſeek after thoſe, which are at the right hand of God, where is fullneſs of joy, and pleaſures for evermore.</hi> Oh, if we could but draw the curtains of Heaven, and look into the <hi>Sanctum Sanctorum,</hi> and ſee the joyes, and the glory <hi>that there is layd up for thoſe that ſeek it,</hi> we would never care for the earth more, we would never care for this world more; the very plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of the Court would ſeem vile unto us, the treaſures of wickedneſs we would trample un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der our feet; all our thoughts would tend up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:29984:27"/>all our care, and ſtudy in the ſeeking of thoſe things that are above, <hi>where Chriſt ſitteth at the right hand of God,</hi> and where we hope one day to ſit on the right hand of Chriſt. St. <hi>Paul</hi> had that happineſs that never man had but he, <hi>To be rapt up into the third Heavens, and there ſaw thoſe things,</hi> which here we Preach of, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn again. But ſee what effect it wrought upon him, it took him cleere off of the world, his life ever after was nothing, but a <hi>Cupio diſſolvi, &amp; eſſe cum Christo: Cupio diſſolvi &amp; eſſe cum Chriſto: I deſire to be diſſolved, and to be with Chriſt: I deſire to be diſſolved, and to be with Chriſt.</hi> All the honour of his Apoſtleſhip, the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of his miracles, the high reputation that he was in amongſt the Nations, for his great learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and wiſedom; for his works, miracles, and powerful Preachings, were all nothing, all theſe could not ſatisfie him; nothing could now con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent him, but <hi>Cupio diſſolvi, &amp; eſſe cum Chriſto: I deſire to be diſſolved, and to be with Chriſt.</hi> And why was this high favour vouchſafed to this Apoſtle, <hi>to be thus rapt up into the third Heavens,</hi> and after he had ſeen thoſe glorious things, then to return again; but that he might be an expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimentall Preacher to the world of all thoſe
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:29984:27"/>things that there he ſaw, and here we ſpeak of? No marvaile if the Fathers of old, St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> St. <hi>Jerome,</hi> St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> St. <hi>Bernard,</hi> &amp;c. were ſo much and often in contemplation, heavenly me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations, ſpirituall ejaculations, as witnes their <hi>Manuels, Enchiridions, Soliloquies, Monuments of their Devotion left among us;</hi> by theſe did they live in communion with God; upon theſe did their ſoules ſweetly feed, and feaſt, as upon meat to eat, which the world knew not of: By theſe they even lived in Heaven, while they were on Earth, and in ſtead of Men, converſed with An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels: Beloved, we have ſoules, as well as bodies, and conſiſt as well of celeſtiall, as of terreſtriall ſubſtance; why ſhould our earthly part be more powerful to draw us <hi>downward</hi> to the vile things here below, then our heavenly part <hi>to carry us up to the pretious things that are above? where our hopes are, where our Inheritance lyes, where our happineſs is, where our Chriſt is, and where we hope ſhortly to be with him in Glory.</hi> Whither the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty of his infinite mercy bring us, through the Merit and Obedience of this <hi>One</hi> in my Text, our Mediator: To whom therefore be all Honour, Power, and Prayſe for evermore: <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
